Guide to the Robertson family papers, 1820-1907.
Robertson family papers, 1820-1907.
- Series I. Correspondence
  - August 12 - October 26, 1846 (11 items)
    - From Jacob Abbott of New York to SR, August 12, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 9)
      Abbott is not certain whether or not he will be able to attend an Institute scheduled for early October. He thanks SR for the positive information and says that he will send a definite answer when he is able to.
    - From C. La. (?) Ford, Medina to SR of Ithaca, August 15, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 9)
      Ford is not certain whether or not he will be able to speak on Anatomy and Physiology at an Institute in the early part of October
    - From A.J. Tompkins of Lansing inviting SR to their school celebration, September 11, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 9)
    - From Alonzo Wynkoop, Chemung, to SR of Ithaca, September 21, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 9)
      Wynkoop asks for SR's assistance in finding qualified teachers to lead an Institute.
    - From Horace Mann, Boston to SR, September 26, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 9)
      Mann sends his regrets and says he will not be able to attend their Institute. He commends SR for the work he is doing.
    - Printed circular from Andrews and Boyle, Publishers, N.Y.C. to SR, September 26, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 9)
      Requesting the names and mailing addresses of all the town superintendents in the county and all of the teachers in the county. Andrews and Boyle are publishing a weekly newspaper, the Anglo Saxon, and hope to interest the superintendents and teachers in becoming subscribers.
    - From Jacob Abbott, N.Y., to SR, October 5, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 9)
      Abbott will be able to visit the Institute.
    - Printed circular from 0. C. Gardiner of N.Y.C. to SR, Supt. of Common Schools, Tompkins County, October 8, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 9)
      Circular is a testimonial for the magazine American Quarterly Journal of Agriculture and Science; hand written letter {pages 2-3) is sent to encourage SR to subscribe to magazine.
    - From Oliver Dyer of New York to SR, October 8, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 9)
      Mr. Augustus Boyle will not be able to address 'the Teachers' Institute on Phonographics and sends his regrets.
    - From P. S. Ely, Hector, to SR of Ithaca, October 16, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 9)
      Ely's visit to Ithaca has been postponed a week. The Burdett School is in need of a teacher and Ely suggests that SR send them one.
    - Form letter from N. S. Benton, Supt. Common Schools, Secretary's Office, Dept. of Common Schools, Albany to County Superintendent SR, October 26, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 9)
      Blank reports for district trustees are available.
  - February 19 - October 14, 1847 (11 items)
    - Form letter from Delphian Institute of Union College, Schenectady to SR as a former member, February 19, 1847 (Box 243 1, Folder 10)
      Asking for a donation of either money or books to keep, in the Institute's attempt to fit up a reading room.
    - From Alonzo Wynkoop, County Supt. of Chemung, to SR, Ithaca, March 15, 1847 (Box 243 1, Folder 10)
      Three counties, Tompkins, Steuben and Chemung are planning a union Teachers' Institute to which all the neighboring counties are being invited. The letter from Wynkoop is to inform SR of what has been planned so far; who the principal speakers will be, a sample of the notice to appear in the newspapers (handwritten).
    - From Alonzo Wynkoop, Chemung, to SR, Ithaca, April 10, 1847 (Box 243 1, Folder 10)
      Letter gives SR more news about the union Institute informing him that notices have been sent to newspapers. Wynkoop has had no definite answer from those whom he has asked to address the Institute, If all else fails, he will call upon SR to deliver an address. (first mention is made of Robertson being married as Wynkoop says ".. .and shall hope to meet your bride,... .")
    - From N. S. Benton, State of New York Secretary's Office, Dept. of Common Schools, Albany to SR, May 6, 1847 (Box 243 1, Folder 10)
      Letter says that land is liable to assessment by a district if it lies partially within that district and if the owner/occupant resides on the land in that particular district.
    - From B. F. Winegar, a member of SR's fraternity, Sigma Phi, at Union College, to SR, June 23, 1847 (Box 243 1, Folder 10)
      The fraternity needs donations from members to build a membership hall. This letter contains second mention of SR having recently married.
    - From Cyrus Robertson, Albion, Michigan, to his brother, SR, July 24, 1847 (Box 243 1, Folder 10)
    - Printed circular from N. S. Benton, Secretary's Office, Dept. of Common Schools, Albany, to County Supt. SR, September 1, 1847 (Box 243 1, Folder 10)
      The circular contains information pertaining to the reduction of the amount of gratuity allowed to pupils.
    - From Benj[amin] Cook, Penn Yan to SR, October 4, 1847 (Box 243 1, Folder 10)
      Cook will not be able to attend the whole of an Institute to lecture and teach Phonography but will be present for the second week.
    - From J. S. (?) Holmes, Deputy Supt. of Common Schools, State of New York, Secretary's Office, Dept. of Common Schools, to SR, October 7, 1847 (Box 243 1, Folder 10)
      Letter concerns a discrepancy concerning sums of money received during the current year, which appear in SR's abstract of Town Superintendent Reports.
    - From James Redfield of Lyons, County Supt. for Wayne County to SR, October 14, 1847 (Box 243 1, Folder 10)
      Introducing Dr. Calvin Cutler, author of a book on physiology; on same sheet.
    - From Calvin Cutler, Ithaca to SR, October 19, 1847 (Box 243 1, Folder 10)
      Sending SR a copy of the above mentioned book.
  - January 16, 1848 - June 30, 1852
    - From Philip and Sarah Robertson, Conneaut, Ohio, to SR, January 16, 1848 (Box 243 1, Folder 11)
    - From B. R. King & P. R. King, Middleport, N.Y. to their brother and sister, SR and ? (his wife?) sleighing; RR correspondence, March 26, 1848 (Box 243 1, Folder 11)
    - From W. Van Wyck, Union College to SR, March 27, 1848 (Box 243 1, Folder 11)
      The letter asks for funds for the finishing of the Conclave hall for the Sigma Phi fraternity at Union College.
    - From H. (?) McGonegal, Baldwinsville, to SR, July 11, 1848 (Box 243 1, Folder 11)
      Asking SR for a recommendation for a teaching position.
    - From O. O. Wickham, Clinton Hall (pm Williamsburg), N.Y. to SR, November 16, 1849 (Box 243 1, Folder 11)
      Wickham requests a list of the names and addresses of the teachers in the area so that he may send them ".. .some valuable information which will be to their advantage and advance the cause of education."
    - Printed circular from Association of Former Students of Cortland Academy to SR, June 30, 1852 (Box 243 1, Folder 11)
      Asks for donations for a fund to be given to Mr. Wollworth, by his former pupils upon his resignation.
  - Undated (5 items)
    - From Thomas (?) Dwight, Albany, to SR, July 17 (Box 243 1, Folder 12)
      Concerns an Institute not being held. There is also mention made of an attack upon the present school system being made at a teachers' convention.
    - From Thomas (?) Dwight, Albany, to SR, August 2 (Box 243 1, Folder 12)
      Dwight is asking SR for information of the upcoming Tompkins County Institute.
    - From Peter Selover, Homer, to SR, November 4 (Box 243 1, Folder 12)
      The author of the letter had been promised a letter he did not receive. He is now appealing to SR for a certificate and/or a letter of recommendation.
    - Printed circular advertising an arithmetic series, Undated (Box 243 1, Folder 12)
    - Printed circular advertising Mitchell's Map Establishment, Undated (Box 243 1, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous Letters and Receipts (not involving Smith Robertson) 1821 - 1850 (20 items)
  - From Adjt. General W. L. Marcy, Troy, to General Samuel Hatheway, Homer, October 29, 1821 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
    General Marcy has been asked to give an opinion about whether or not officers who did not parade their companies on a certain required date should be punished. If they did not know that they were required to perform a duty, then they can not be punished for failing to fulfill the obligation. Note: Xerox copy placed in Hatheway Family Papers, Ace. #2281.
  - Receipt for pay as teacher in District #4, town and county unnamed; signed by Israel Roberts, April 28, 1828 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
  - From Ebby Hyde, Farmer [Interlaken], to Doctor Frederick Hyde, Cortland Village, March 4, 1836 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
    Augustus (?) has just left Ebby Hyde's after a visit. Ebby says that he regrets that Frederick could not have been there at the same time as Augustus but says it was not possible. Ebby talks of a trip he is soon to start upon and says he is looking forward to Frederick's visit.
  - From G. Woodruff, Buffalo, to Dr. Frederick Hyde, Cortlandville, July 14, 1837 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
    Personal letter containing family news and other items of gossip. Woodruff teases Hyde about his (Hyde's) "unpatriotic bachelorhood."
  - From C. F. Woodruff, Ithaca, to father (step-father?, father-in-law?) P. Pelton of Monticello, N.Y, July 20, 1842 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
    Regarding trip by stagecoach from Monticello to Ithaca.
  - From J. W. French of Albion, New York, to Mr. E. B. Walsworth, of Walworth, Wayne Co, December 18, 1843 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
    Concerning a report to be made out re the Walworth Academy of which Walsworth is principal.
  - From James S. McRie, Union College, to E. B.. Walsworthth, January 22, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
    Asking for a teaching position at the Walworth Academy where Walsworth is principal.
  - From George Loomis of Genesee Wesleyan Seminary, Lima, Livingston Co. to E. B. Walsworth, February 21, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
    Saying that visit to "Lyceum" at Walworth, Wayne Co. at present would not be possible.
  - From Joseph Rosenkrans of Fort Plain to Mr. Walsworth of Union College, May 30, 1844 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
    Request that Walsworth deliver sermon in place of Rosenkrans while he (Rosenkrans) must be away.
  - From Caleb Clark, Truxton, to Dr. Frederick Hyde, Cortland (ville), September 30, 1845 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
    Clark is ill and wishes Dr. Hyde to prescribe some medicine for him.
  - From John Foster, Union College, to E. B. Walsworth at Auburn Theological Seminary, May 26, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
    In doubt as to date of Auburn Commencement and "propriety" of his [Foster's] addressing the body.
  - From Silas C. Brown, W. Bloomfield, to his nephew E. B. Walsworth, Auburn, N.Y. Family matters, June 12, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
  - From Rev. E. G. Townsend, Sackets Harbor, to E. Walsworth, Auburn. Personal news and comment, December 17, 1846 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
  - From H. W. Parker, Mexico, N.Y., to E. B. Walsworth, Auburn Theological Seminary, March 25, 1847 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
    (Rev.) Parker wishes someone to substitute for him for four Sabbaths and asks Walsworth's assistance in securing someone.
  - From Albert West, Troy to Ira G. Fellows, November 7, 1847 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
    Will be 21 11/8 (b. 1826). Visit to N.Y.C. - theatre-going, attending Trinity Church.
  - From Albert West, Troy, to Ira G. Fellows, Pulaski. Mutual friends and daily activities, May 7, 1848 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
  - From Henry L. Young of Avon, to Rev. E. B. Walsworth, Union Theological Seminary, N.Y, May 8, 1848 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
    Is invited to assume Presbyterian pastorate at Avon. "This is missionary ground... ."
  - From Albert West, Troy, to Ira G. Fellows. Personal news, November 5, 1848 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
  - From Albert West, Troy, to Ira G. Fellows, February 4, 1850 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
    Social news -- sleigh rides.
  - From Albert West, Troy, to Ira G. Fellows, Pulaski, April 12, 1850 (Box 243 1, Folder 13)
    Maple sugar making news from California; "'tell the boys to let well enough alone and stay at home."
- Miscellaneous Madison and Chenango County School District Records (3 items)
  - Warrant from Almon Baker, trustee of School District #8, Cazenovia, Madison County ordering him to receive school taxes, July 13, 1884 (Box 243 1, Folder 14)
    Includes a list of taxable inhabitants and amounts they owe. 1 item (2 pcs.)
  - Order to Tax Collector to pay wages earned by Addie Warner as teacher in School District #9, Town of Lincklaen, Chenango County, November 18, 1895 (Box 243 1, Folder 14)
  - A handwritten catalogue of books (15 vols.) belonging to School District #2, Town of Lincklaen, Undated (Box 243 1, Folder 14)